What do you do if you're suddenly
diagnosed with stage 4 colon cancer?
You're scared. You get all these
different opinions thrown at you. You're
in a state of confusion. Today, I want
to give you some relief on that. I'm not
going to get into statistics. I want to
get into strategies. And one of the
biggest questions that people ask their
doctors when they have cancer is, "What
do I eat?" And the answer is usually,
"It doesn't really matter." And that is
so far from the truth because you can
either feed cancer or you can stress
cancer or starve cancer. Cancer itself
is very sick. It's living on the edge.
And so what we want to do is we want a
strategy that leverages everything you
do to overcome that. So we'll talk about
nutrition. We'll talk about foods. I
also want to talk about prolonged
fasting because some people can't do
that. They have too much weight loss. So
then what do they do? I have a solution
for that. You really need to know also
the four main causes of colon cancer and
what's unique about colon cancer. So,
I'm going to cover that as well. One
thing about cancer and other chronic
diseases is it does not happen
overnight. It takes decades to develop.
And so, if you don't have cancer and
you're watching this video, make mental
notes on what I'm going to say because
this is going to be very important to
avoid cancer. Let's talk about what's
unique about cancer. Number one, cancer
is heterogeneous. What does that mean?
That means that cancer is not one
disease. There's many different types of
cancer which relate to different genetic
weaknesses, to using different fuels, to
affecting the immune system differently.
That is why you cannot use one single
diet for all cancers. But I'm going to
show you what you should be using. I
already mentioned this right here.
Cancer is very, very sick. It's living
on the edge, but we want to know its
weaknesses. And one really big weakness
is this right here. They're
metabolically inflexible. What do I mean
by that? It means they have a very
difficult time going from one fuel to a
different fuel source. So going from
glucose to ketones or fat, they have a
difficult time doing that. The great
majority of the population is not
metabolically flexible. In fact, with my
own body and my own health, I was not
very metabolically flexible. I had to
correct that. So, we will cover that as
well. We want to stress it out and keep
pressure on that cancer. So, it has no
resources so it can't keep growing and
taking over. As soon as the cancer
finally adapts to a certain diet, we
switch it over to a different diet. The
other thing that's unique about cancer
is that the origin of cancer comes from
damaged mitochondria.
Mitochondria are the energy factories of
the cell. What happens with cancer is
when the mitochondria becomes damaged.
As a survival mechanism, the body will
then switch to an ancient pathway called
glycolysis. This is a plan B with fuel
for cancer. When the cancer cell goes
into this mode here, it cannot produce
very much energy. So what does it do? it
starts going crazy and starts growing
really fast to hog a lot of your energy
and steal your resources. That's what
happens with cancer. But to compensate,
they're hogging a lot of glucose. This
is why in a PET scan, they're scanning
areas of the body where there's this
high level of glucose. That's usually
where the cancer cell is. So, the goal
is not necessarily to starve the cancer,
okay? And I'm going to tell you why.
It's to stress
the cancer,
okay? Stress it out to the point where
it can't keep growing. It starts
shriveling up and then it dies off. This
is why we're going to rotate the diets.
And also, I highly recommend you do many
things at once to deal with this cancer,
not just one single thing. Whether you
decide to do chemo, radiation, or not,
I'm not here to tell you what to do. I'm
just giving you additional data because
with cancer, it's desperate and it will
do all sorts of things to overcome the
barriers. Even when you get chemo or
radiation therapy, you'll usually kill
the majority of cancer, but the cancer
cells that don't die become stronger and
they can come back and now the chemo
doesn't work anymore. So, now let's
cover where does cancer actually come
from. Number one, chronic insulin
resistance. This is why a diabetic for
example is more at risk for cancer than
other types of conditions because of
this insulin resistance where the body
can't really absorb insulin. So the
pancreas makes more initially and it
starts making more and more. So all this
extra insulin acts like a growth factor.
It can make things grow like tumors.
When you have insulin resistance, this
is where you get metabolic
inflexibility. And also on the flip
side, if you want to correct metabolic
inflexibility, you have to correct
insulin resistance. This is why going on
a low carb ketogenic diet is so so
important. Number two, chronic
inflammation.
Cancer travels or migrates into areas of
Inflammation is a state where you don't
have much oxygen. Let's take a smoker
for example, right? If someone's a
chronic smoker, they're going to create
a lack of oxygen in their lungs because
of all the damage in the scar tissue.
Number three, chronic microbiome
disruption. If someone has a history of
damage in the microbiome from junk
foods, antibiotics,
they're going to be more susceptible to
getting cancer because the microbes
really protect you against cancer in
many different ways, which I'm going to
cover a little bit of that in this
presentation as well in a bit. And then
we have number four, chronic toxicity.
Now, this could be alcohol, could be
smoking, pesticides, insecticides,
herbicides, fungicides, it could be many
different things that are toxic, but
it's the chronic exposure to toxicity.
So, of course, the more you combine
these, the more you're going to get
cancer. Now, what's interesting is all
of these things here are the root causes
of mitochondrial damage. Now, some
people say, "Well, what if I'm
genetically susceptible?" Yeah, you
might be, but it also takes
environmental things to push it over the
edge. Just because you have a genetic
weakness does not mean you're going to
get cancer. I want to just talk a little
bit about the colon for a second. Colon
cells, okay? Because colon cells are
very unique in that they will get their
fuel from something called butyrate. And
butyrate is a chemical that comes from a
microbe eating fiber and then they
produce this chemical called butyrate
and that's like the primary fuel for the
colon cell. And so butyrate strengthens
the lining. It helps feed the colon.
It's anti-inflammatory.
And this is where people get, you know,
oh, you need to consume more fiber to
prevent cancer. But there's a paradox
here, okay? Fiber can also make things
worse. Fiber can actually inflame your
colon. Fiber can make you bloated. And
this is why people that get bloating and
SIBO, it's called small intestinal
bacterial overgrowth, do very well with
the carnivore diet, which is like no
fiber, no plants, no nuts, no beans, no
grains, anything. Okay. If you had a
history of antibiotics starting as a
child or maybe you were never breastfed,
so you didn't have those normal microbes
from the mother,
that can be a problem later in life
because now the microbes are not
balanced in a way to deal with the
fiber. And a lot of people, they don't
have the microbes to even break down the
fiber. So this is why you can have two
people eat the exact same thing. One
person feels like they're pregnant, the
other person is just fine. It's all
about the microbes and what microbes you
have and where those microbes are
located. And I have a lot of videos on
that topic and I will put some links
down below. Now, the one thing you need
to know, the worse the cancer is as far
as prognosis, the more you need to do
it's called prolonged fasting because
prolonged fasting give the cancer cells
no fuel and a lot of stress. And I've
had people do it up to like even 30 to
40 days and actually get rid of their
cancer. So what can you do? The fasting
mimicking diet. It mimics fasting as far
as the results because you are consuming
some calories between 700 to a little
bit over a,000 calories a day, but
you're going low protein,
low carb, and low fat. If you don't have
cancer, you should start doing smaller
prolong fasting cycles, whether it's
three days or 5 days every so often
because that's one of the most powerful
things to kill cancer. Cancer cannot
live in a fasting state. A couple other
really important things to add to the
mix are high doses of vitamin D3,
minimally 30,000 IUs of vitamin D3. But
vitamin D is the most important nutrient
for your immune system. It's also going
to help support the mitochondria. Now,
if you can be outside in the sun, that
would be awesome as well because the sun
doesn't just give you vitamin D, but it
can give you other things, too, like
infrared, which actually is going to
heal the cells from a different angle.
And also oxygen to get as much oxygen as
you can whether it's a hyperbaric
chamber or it's basically exercise
walking very important because cancer
doesn't like oxygen.
Okay. So now let's talk about
this rotating diet. And just so you know
everything that I say I'm going to
detail in a download for you so you'll
have that all in writing so you don't
have to write any of this down. For your
first meal, it might be vegetable soup
with good amount of salt in there. And
then you might add some olive oil or
avocado oil, coldressed, very important.
Your second meal might be steamed
zucchini, spinach with a small portion
of olives or an avocado, and that's
pretty much what you can eat. Now,
you'll have electrolytes and
supplements, but it's not a lot of food,
but it's something. And the reason why
you're going low fat is in an advanced
state of cancer, it's not just glucose
that that cancer can survive on. It can
also survive on fats and ketones. It'll
use those as well. So this first diet is
basically just kind of really
restricting the resources and the
available foods for that cancer to live
on. But it's only 3 to 5 days, but
you're not going to do fish, meat, or
eggs. You're not going to do cheese. And
you're definitely not going to do grains
or sugar. After 3 to 5 days, you're
going to go into phase 2. And phase 2 is
between 7 and 14 days. This is pretty
much going to support your colon, and
it's going to be moderate protein,
moderate fat. One fat that you can have
is the omega-3 fats from fish oil, like
especially cive oil. You can do that.
And then you're going to control your
carbohydrates. All the foods that I'm
going to recommend have various things
that actually help reduce cancer. They
have polyphenols, different things in
them. So all these ingredients will help
support the reduction of cancer in
different ways. Now phase three is for 3
to 5 days. Okay? A little bit shorter,
but now we're going to actually increase
the protein. We'll keep the fat
moderate. Now, why don't we go high in
the fat? Because anytime you have
advanced stage any type of cancer,
that's when the cancer can start living
off of ketones. Not ketones from your
own fat. It's two different types of
ketones. So, I'm not going to get into
specific of that, but you don't have to
worry about the ketones from fasting.
Just have to worry about going too high
with the fat. So, now we're getting into
6 to 8 ounces and then moderate protein
and we're going to go low carb. So,
what's going to happen? the cancer is
going to start to want to adapt to that,
but we're going to then switch it after
3 to 5 days. So, we're just going to
take these three things and keep
rotating them and rotating them and not
give the cancer a chance to adapt.
That's what the strategy is. Some key
nutrients, vitamin D3, zinc, omega-3
fatty acids, polyphenols, turmeric,
cruciferous vegetables, herbs and spices
are good, green tea is going to be very
important, fermented vegetables like
sauerkraut if you can tolerate it. We're
going to support the body. We're going
to support the mitochondria. We're going
to support the immune system. We're
going to support your muscle. We're
going to fix fermentation. And of
course, I need to give you a disclaimer.
Check with your doctor before
implementing any of this. But I think
most doctors will look at this and
think, "Wow, this makes common sense. I
don't see anything that would interfere
with whatever treatment they're giving
you." I have a free download that I want
to give to you. This free download is my
daily routine in a checklist. This is a
routine that I use every day to feel
like I'm 18 years old, even though I'm
60 years old. And I want to give it to
you for free. And so there's a little
link down below. Click it and definitely
download that. Now, for those of you
that have cancer or don't have cancer,
the million-dollar question is, how do
you fix this right here, which is
probably one of the most common things
that people have that create the most
problems, chronic insulin resistance?
And for that information, it's right in
this video right here. Watch this right
now. Check it out.